Preliminary guide to the Martin Sebastian Soria Papers
Yale University Arts Library
Martin Sebastian Soria papers
1940-1960
ART 27
Yale University Arts Library
11
(11 boxes)
The papers consist of photographs, correspondence, research notes, and clippings assembled by art historian Martin Soria and documenting his studies of art and architecture in Europe, particularly Spain.
Soria, Martin
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the office of George Kubler, 1990. Transferred from the Catalog Dept., SML, 2007. Transferred from Manuscripts and Archives (MSSA) to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Martin Sebastian Soria was born in Berlin, Germany, on July 3, 1911. He received a B.A. degree from the University of Madrid, and M.A. and Ph.D. degrees from Harvard. Soria also studied at the University of Zurich. He was an instructor at Princeton from 1944-1946, and a member of the art department at Michigan State University from 1948 until his death in Brussels on February 15, 1961.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of photographs, correspondence, research notes, and clippings assembled by art historian Martin Soria and documenting his studies of art and architecture in Europe, particularly Spain.
Arrangement
Preliminary box listing only.
Art -- History; Painting, Spanish; Art historians; Soria, Martin
- Box listing
  Scope and Contents
  Folders 1-167 consist of items, primarily photographs, which were individually numbered and indexed by Martin Soria. Although photographs comprise the bulk of the material, other items, such as correspondence, notes, and printed material, have been included and are numbered and indexed. Additional research files and visual resources are found in boxes 9-11.
  Arrangement
  The photographs in folders 1-106 are arranged by artist and can be accessed by referring to the index prepared under the direction of George Kubler. Artists are listed alphabetically. Each entry consists of the name of the artist, birth and death dates, origin and school, folder number, and photograph number. Material in these folders may also be accessed by utilizing a two page school of painting index. A detailed list of the photographs is included in most of the folders.
  The contents of folders 107-167 were originally housed in four letter boxes labeled A-D. The items were removed from the letter boxes and foldered. A separate index exists for these folders. The index consists of the photograph number, title of work or a short description of the item, artist, location, and notes. Each page of the index corresponds to one folder. The contents of folders 107-116, originally housed in letter box A, did not have a detailed listing, and therefore, broad folder titles were used for identification. Folders 117-166 have detailed listings as described above. Folder 167 contains unidentified contents.
  - Folders 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 1-15)
    Complete index to all folders also available in Box 1.
  - Folders 16-28 (Box 2, Folder 16-28)
  - Folders 29-42 (Box 3, Folder 29-42)
  - Folders 43-55 (Box 4, Folder 43-55)
  - Folders 56-73 (Box 5, Folder 56-73)
  - Folders 74-84 (Box 6, Folder 74-84)
  - Folders 85-106 (Box 7, Folder 85-106)
  - Folders 107-151 (Box 8, Folder 107-151)
  - Folders 152-167 (Box 9, Folder 152-167)
  - Unsorted materials: photographs, notes, correspondence, and clippings, 1950s-1960s undated (Box 9)
  - Microfilm: "The 18th Century Retable in the South of Spain, Portugal, and Mexico," by Joseph A. Baird, Jr.; doctoral thesis, 1951 (Box 10)
  - Microfilm: "Francesco Nomé Detto Monsù Desiderio," Raffaello Causa, undated (Box 10)
  - Unidentified fragments of microfilm, undated (Box 10)
  - Six boxes of negative files, 1947-1951 (Box 10)
  - Loose negatives, undated (Box 10)
  - Slides, undated (Box 10)
  - Loose photographs, undated (Box 10)
  - Notes on Simon Garcia's bibliography, undated (Box 10)
  - Photographs: Bogota, 1950 (Box 10)
  - Index card file, undated (Box 10)
  - 16 note pads, undated (Box 10)
  - Glass negatives, undated (Box 10)
  - Photographs and writings of the art of Juan de Valdés Leal, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Unsorted materials: photographs, notes, correspondence, and clippings, 1950s-1960s undated (Box 11)
  - Writings by Martin Soria: reprints, 1940s-1960s undated (Box 11)
  - Eliab Metcalf material: correspondence, photographs, printed material, slides, late 1950s-1960 undated (Box 11)